<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<item>
  <title>A time-sensitive similarity measure for scanpaths</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2007). A time-sensitive similarity measure for scanpaths. In R. Kliegl, &amp; R. Engbert, Proceedings of the 14th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: Journal of Eye Movement Research.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2007ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A new method for analyzing eye movements in reading that is sensitive to spatial and temporal patterns in sequences of fixations</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2008). A new method for analyzing eye movements in reading that is sensitive to spatial and temporal patterns in sequences of fixations. In P. Gordon, Proceedings of the 21th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 118). Chapel Hill, NC, USA: University of North Caroline at Chapel Hill.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2008CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Individual differences in scanpaths and reanalysis strategies while reading temporarily ambiguous sentences</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2009). Individual differences in scanpaths and reanalysis strategies while reading temporarily ambiguous sentences. In S. Liversedge, Proceedings of the 15th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Southampton, UK: Journal of Eye Movement Research.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2009ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Readers use different strategies to recover from garden-paths</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2009). Readers use different strategies to recover from garden-paths. In , Proceedings of the Summer School on Embodied Language Games and Construction Grammar (pp. ). Cortona, Italy: .</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2009Cortona</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Analyzing spatio-temporal patterns in eye movements: A method and software</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2009). Analyzing spatio-temporal patterns in eye movements: A method and software. In M. Traxler, &amp; T. Swaab, Proceedings of the 22th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: University of California, Davis.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2009CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TELIDA: A package for manipulation and visualization of timed linguistic data</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Baumann, T., &amp; Schlangen, D.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Baumann, T., &amp; Schlangen, D. (2009). TELIDA: A package for manipulation and visualization of timed linguistic data. In , Proceedings of the SIGDIAL 2009 Conference: The 10th Annual Meeting of the Special Interest Group on Discourse and Dialogue (pp. 302–305). London, UK: .</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2009SIGDIAL</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Choice of saccade detection algorithm has a considerable impact on eye tracking measures</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus (2009). Choice of saccade detection algorithm has a considerable impact on eye tracking measures. In S. Liversedge, Proceedings of the 15th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Southampton, UK: Journal of Eye Movement Research.</description>
  <guid>Malsburg2009ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Integration difficulty and expectation-based syntactic comprehension</title>
  <author>Vasishth, S., Drenhaus, H., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Vasishth, S., Drenhaus, H., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2010). Integration difficulty and expectation-based syntactic comprehension. In D. Bemis, J. Brennan, S. Dikker, I. Livitz, A. Marantz, B. McElree, L. Pylkkänen, …, Proceedings of the 23th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 111). New York City, NY, USA: New York University.</description>
  <guid>VasishthEtAl2010CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reanalysis strategies in temporarily ambiguous sentence -- A scanpath analysis</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2010). Reanalysis strategies in temporarily ambiguous sentence -- A scanpath analysis. In D. Bemis, J. Brennan, S. Dikker, I. Livitz, A. Marantz, B. McElree, L. Pylkkänen, …, Proceedings of the 23th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 32). New York City, NY, USA: New York University.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2010CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Strategies for dealing with attachment ambiguities in Spanish</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2011). Strategies for dealing with attachment ambiguities in Spanish. In , Proceedings of the 10th Symposium of Psycholinguistics (pp. ). San Sebastián, Spain: .</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2011XSymp</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Eye-movement strategies for dealing with garden-path sentences</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2011). Eye-movement strategies for dealing with garden-path sentences. In A. Fernald, M. C. Frank, D. Jurafsky, I. A. Sag, &amp; T. Wasow, Proceedings of the 24th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 205–206). Stanford, CA, USA: Stanford University.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2011CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What is the scanpath signature of syntactic reanalysis?</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2011). What is the scanpath signature of syntactic reanalysis? Journal of Memory and Language, 65(2), 109–127. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jml.2011.02.004

Which repair strategy does the language system deploy when it gets garden-pathed, and what can regressive eye movements in reading tell us about reanalysis strategies? Several influential eye-tracking studies on syntactic reanalysis (Frazier \&amp; Rayner, 1982; Meseguer, Carreiras, \&amp; Clifton, 2002; Mitchell, Shen, Green, \&amp; Hodgson, 2008) have addressed this question by examining scanpaths, i.e., sequential patterns of eye fixations. However, in the absence of a suitable method for analyzing scanpaths, these studies relied on simplified dependent measures that are arguably ambiguous and hard to interpret. We address the theoretical question of repair strategy by developing a new method that quantifies scanpath similarity. Our method reveals several distinct fixation strategies associated with reanalysis that went undetected in a previously published data set (Meseguer et al., 2002). One prevalent pattern suggests re-parsing of the sentence, a strategy that has been discussed in the literature (Frazier \&amp; Rayner, 1982); however, readers differed tremendously in how they orchestrated the various fixation strategies. Our results suggest that the human parsing system non-deterministically adopts different strategies when confronted with the disambiguating material in garden-path sentences.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2011</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A scanpath measure reveals effects of age of reader and syntactic complexity of sentences</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S. (2011). A scanpath measure reveals effects of age of reader and syntactic complexity of sentences. In F. Vitu, E. Castet, &amp; L. Goffart, Proceedings of the 16th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. 254). Marseilles, France: Journal of Eye Movement Research.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2011ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tense morphology in german agrammatism: The production of regular, irregular and mixed verbs</title>
  <author>Marusch, T., von der Malsburg, Titus, Bastiaanse, R., &amp; Burchert, F.</author>
  <description>Marusch, T., von der Malsburg, Titus, Bastiaanse, R., &amp; Burchert, F. (2012). Tense morphology in german agrammatism: The production of regular, irregular and mixed verbs. The Mental Lexicon, 7(3), 351–380. http://dx.doi.org/10.1075/ml.7.3.05mar

This study investigates tense morphology in agrammatic aphasia and the predictions of two accounts on processing of regular and irregular verbs: the Dual Mechanism model, that is, for aphasic data, the Declarative/Procedural model, and the Single Mechanism approach. The production of regular, irregular and mixed verbs in the present, simple past and past participle (present perfect) was tested in German by means of a sentence completion task with a group of seven speakers with agrammatic aphasia. The results show a difference between regular verbs and irregular verbs. Mixed verbs were equally difficult as irregular verbs. A frequency effect was found for irregular verbs but not for regular and mixed verbs. A significant difference among the correctness scores for present tense and simple past forms was found. Simple past and past participle were significantly more difficult than present tense. Error types were characterized by pure infinitive responses and time reference errors. Neither of the above accounts is sufficient to explain these results. Correctness scores and error patterns for mixed verbs suggest that such minor lexical patterns can be useful in finding new evidence in the debate on morphological processing. The findings also highlight time reference as well as language specific characteristics need to be taken into consideration.</description>
  <guid>MaruschEtAl2012</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpaths in reading are informative about sentence processing</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Kliegl, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Kliegl, R. (2012). Scanpaths in reading are informative about sentence processing. In P. B. Michael Carl, &amp; K. K. Choudhary, Proceedings of the First Workshop on Eye-tracking and Natural Language Processing (pp. 37–53). Mumbai, India: The COLING 2012 organizing committee.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2012Coling</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Determinants of scanpath regularity in reading</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S. (2012). Determinants of scanpath regularity in reading. In D. Bradley, E. Fernández, &amp; J. D. Fodor, Proceedings of the 25th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 82). New York City, NY, USA: CUNY Graduate School and University Center.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2012CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpath phenomena in reading: An investigation of scanpath effects in syntactic ambiguity resolution and in general reading</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus (2012). Scanpath phenomena in reading: An investigation of scanpath effects in syntactic ambiguity resolution and in general reading (Doctoral dissertation). University of Potsdam, .

A pioneering study in reading research \cite{FrazierRayner1982} demonstrated that scanpaths, sequences of fixations of the eyes, are informative about sentence processing mechanisms. Nevertheless, analyses of scanpaths have not gained much traction in reading research. We conjecture that one reason contributing to this state of affairs is the relative difficulty of analyzing scanpaths and a lack of suitable analytical tools. Most studies used simplifying measures such as the probability of a regressive eye movement on a critical word of the sentence. Although this approach has been successful in many cases, there are research question that have resisted these conventional methods. One such question is: how does the human sentence processor recover when a word indicates that the interpretation of a sentence maintained so far is incorrect? To attack this problem, we developed a new method for analyzing scanpath patterns and showed that re-processing of the sentence is a common strategy---a possibility that had been dismissed in earlier literature \cite{FrazierRayner1982}. However, it appears that rereading is not the only available strategy and that readers differ quite a lot in how they orchestrate various strategies. Our experimental data suggests that working memory capacity is one factor influencing the choice of processing strategies. We also used the proposed scanpath method to examine a large corpus of eye movements recorded for a varied set of relatively simple German sentences. This analysis recovered scanpath effects predicted by the literature on aging, sentence processing, and oculo-motor control. The analysis also found new factors determining scanpath trajectories, thus showing that the scanpath method is a valid and productive tool for reading research and perhaps eye movement research in general.</description>
  <guid>Malsburg2012</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incremental processing difficulty in cross-serial and nested verb cluster</title>
  <author>Kobele, G., Lagrou, E., Engelmann, F., von der Malsburg, Titus, Musa, R., Gerth, S., van de Vijver, R., …</author>
  <description>Kobele, G., Lagrou, E., Engelmann, F., von der Malsburg, Titus, Musa, R., Gerth, S., van de Vijver, R., … (2012). Incremental processing difficulty in cross-serial and nested verb cluster. In G. Egidi, U. Hasson, R. Job, F. Vespignani, &amp; R. Zamparelli, Proceedings of the 18th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. 150). Trento, Italy: University of Trento.</description>
  <guid>KobeleEtAl2012AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decomposing electric brain potentials for audification on a matrix of speakers</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Illing, C.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Illing, C. (2013). Decomposing electric brain potentials for audification on a matrix of speakers. In M. Verdicchio, &amp; M. Carvalhais, Proceedings of the first conference on Computation, Communication, Aesthetics and X (pp. 305–307). Bergamo, Italy: The xCoAx 2013 organizing committee.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgIlling2013xCoAx</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What eye movements can tell us about sentence comprehension</title>
  <author>Vasishth, S., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Engelmann, F.</author>
  <description>Vasishth, S., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Engelmann, F. (2013). What eye movements can tell us about sentence comprehension. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Cognitive Science, 4(2), 125–134. http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/wcs.1209

Eye movement data have proven to be very useful for investigating human sentence processing. Eyetracking research has addressed a wide range of questions, such as recovery mechanisms following garden-pathing, the timing of processes driving comprehension, the role of anticipation and expectation in parsing, the role of semantic, pragmatic, and prosodic information, and so on. However, there are some limitations regarding the inferences that can be made on the basis of eye movements. One relates to the nontrivial interaction between parsing and the eye movement control system which complicates the interpretation of eye movement data. Detailed computational models that integrate parsing with eye movement control theories have the potential to unpack the complexity of eye movement data and can therefore aid in the interpretation of eye movements. Another limitation is the difficulty of capturing spatiotemporal patterns in eye movements using the traditional word-based eyetracking measures. Recent research has demonstrated the relevance of these patterns and has shown how they can be analyzed. In this review, we focus on reading, and present examples demonstrating how eye movement data reveal what events unfold when the parser runs into difficulty, and how the parsing system interacts with eye movement control. WIREs Cogn Sci 2013, 4:125–134. doi: 10.1002/wcs.1209For further resources related to this article, please visit the WIREs website.</description>
  <guid>VasishthEtAl2013</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Local coherence and digging-in effects in german</title>
  <author>Paape, D., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Paape, D., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2013). Local coherence and digging-in effects in german. In F. Ferreira, A. Almor, &amp; D. den Ouden, Proceedings of the 26th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 199). Columbia, SC, USA: University of South Carolina.</description>
  <guid>PaapeEtAl2013CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Oscillatory brain dynamics differ between natural reading and serial presentation</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2013). Oscillatory brain dynamics differ between natural reading and serial presentation. In K. Holmqvist, F. Mulvey, &amp; R. Johansson, Proceedings of the 17th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. 187). Lund, Sweden: Journal of Eye Movement Research.

Recent research (Dimigen et al., JEP:G, 2011; Kretzschmar et al., NeuroReport, 2009) shows that fixation-related potentials (FRPs) yield similar results as brain potentials recorded during rapid serial visual presentation (RSVP). We conducted an experiment to see if this correspondence also holds for oscillatory brain dynamics. Participants (N=48) read true (&amp;quot;The Thames flows through London&amp;quot;) and false factual statements (&amp;quot;The Hudson flows through London&amp;quot;). Such violations are known to elicit an N400, a negative-going deflection with a peak around 400 ms, and increased theta and gamma activity (Hagoort, Science, 2004). As expected, we see an N400 in the FRP and increased fixation durations and regression rates in the eye movement record. Moreover, a cluster-permutation test (Maris \&amp; Oostenveld, J Neurosci Methods, 2007) for fixation-related power spectra shows synchronization in the delta range (1-3 Hz) and desynchronization in the upper alpha range (11-13 Hz) but no theta or gamma effects. This is at odds with prior findings and suggests that fixation-related oscillatory EEG changes are not fully comparable to those observed in RSVP. One reason for the diverging results may lie in different processing demands: In RSVP, readers must retrieve earlier parts of the sentence from memory because they cannot make regressions.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2013ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>World-knowledge violations elicit different rhythmic brain activity in natural reading and serial presentation</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2013). World-knowledge violations elicit different rhythmic brain activity in natural reading and serial presentation. In C. Frenck-Mestre, F. Alario, N. Nguyen, P. Blache, &amp; C. Meunier, Proceedings of the 19th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. 32). Marseilles, France: Aix-Marseille Université.

Recent studies (Dimigen et al., JEP:G, 2011; Kretzschmar et al., NeuroReport, 2009) demonstrated the feasibility of investigating fixation-related potentials (FRPs) and that the results are similar to brain potentials recorded during rapid serial visual presentation (RSVP). We conducted an experiment to assess if this correspondence also holds for rhythmic brain activity. To pit our results against ults gained with RSVP, the experiment used sentences that are known to produce reliable effects both in the time domain and in the frequency domain (Hagoort, Science, 2004). Participants (N=48) read freely through true (&amp;apos;The Thames flows through London&amp;apos;) and false statements (&amp;apos;The Hudson flows through London&amp;apos;). Hagoort et al. report an N400, a negative-going deflection in the ERP with a peak around 400 ms, as well as increased theta (4-7 Hz) and gamma (30-70 Hz) activity. During our experiment, participants&amp;apos; eye movements were monitored and their EEG was recorded from 32 electrodes and later evaluated contingent to the first fixation on the critical word. We analyzed the canonical eye-tracking measures with linear mixed-effects models and the EEG with cluster-permutation tests (Maris \&amp; Oostenveld, J Neurosci Methods, 2007) to control for multiple comparisons. As expected, we observed a negativity in the FRP with a centro-parietal distribution and a peak latency of approximately 400 ms. Also as expected, this N400 lined up with increased first fixation durations, gaze durations, and regression rates in the eye movement record (Dambacher \&amp; Kliegl, Brain Res, 2007). Crucially, fixation-related power spectra showed synchronization in the delta range (1-3 Hz) at central electrodes and desynchronization in the upper alpha range (11-13 Hz) at occipito-parietal sites relative to a pre-fixation baseline. None of these effects is reported by Hagoort et al. which suggests that fixation-related EEG changes are at least not fully comparable to those observed in RSVP. One reason for the diverging results could lie in different processing demands: In RSVP, readers must retrieve earlier parts of the sentence from working memory because they cannot make regressions. Increased theta activity reflects this more effortful memory access (Klimesch, Brain Res Rev, 1999). In natural reading, readers can easily move their eyes back to resolve the processing difficulty which facilitates memory access. Our findings question the comparability of results acquired with serial presentation vs. natural reading.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2013AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tempusmorphologie bei deutschen Agrammatikern: Die Sprachproduktion von regulären, irregulären und gemischten Verben</title>
  <author>Marusch, T., von der Malsburg, Titus, Bastiaanse, R., &amp; Burchert, F.</author>
  <description>Marusch, T., von der Malsburg, Titus, Bastiaanse, R., &amp; Burchert, F. (2013). Tempusmorphologie bei deutschen Agrammatikern: Die Sprachproduktion von regulären, irregulären und gemischten Verben. In , Spektrum Patholinguistik (pp. 219–223). Potsdam, Germany: Universitätsverlag Potsdam.

Seit langem wird debattiert, wie reguläre und irreguläre Vergangenheitsformen repräsentiert und verarbeitet werden (Rumelhart \&amp; McClelland, 1986; Pinker \&amp; Prince, 1988). Das Dual- Mechanism-Modell (DMM; Pinker \&amp; Prince, 1988; Clahsen, 1999) nimmt an, dass reguläre und irreguläre Formen von zwei verschiedenen Mechanismen verarbeitet werden. Vertreter des Single-Mechanism Ansatzes gehen alternativ von einem einzigen Mechanismus aus, der sowohl der Verarbeitung von regulären als auch irregulären Verben dient.</description>
  <guid>MaruschEtAl2013</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpaths reveal syntactic underspecification and reanalysis strategies</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2013). Scanpaths reveal syntactic underspecification and reanalysis strategies. Language and Cognitive Processes, 28(10), 1545–1578. http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/01690965.2012.728232

What theories best characterize the parsing processes triggered upon encountering ambiguity, and what effects do these processes have on eye movement patterns in reading? The present eye-tracking study, which investigated processing of attachment ambiguities of an adjunct in Spanish, suggests that readers sometimes underspecify attachment to save memory resources, consistent with the good-enough account of parsing. Our results confirm a surprising prediction of the good-enough account: high-capacity readers commit to an attachment decision more often than low-capacity participants, leading to more errors and a greater need to reanalyze in garden-path sentences. These results emerged only when we separated functionally different types of regressive eye movements using a scanpath analysis; conventional eye-tracking measures alone would have led to different conclusions. The scanpath analysis also showed that rereading was the dominant strategy for recovering from garden-pathing. Our results may also have broader implications for models of reading processes: reanalysis effects in eye movements occurred late, which suggests that the coupling of oculo-motor control and the parser may not always be as tight as assumed in current computational models of eye movements control in reading.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgVasishth2013</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpaths in reading are tractable and informative</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Kliegl, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Kliegl, R. (2013). Scanpaths in reading are tractable and informative. In K. Holmqvist, F. Mulvey, &amp; R. Johansson, Proceedings of the 17th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. 132). Lund, Sweden: Journal of Eye Movement Research.

Pioneering work in reading research has shown that scanpaths in reading can be informative about sentences processing (Frazier, Rayner, 1982). Nevertheless, scanpaths have not gained much traction in reading research. One reason for that may have been a lack of suitable analytical tools. Here, we summarize three recent studies in which we used a new scanpath measure to analyze gaze data from two experimental studies (von der Malsburg, Vasishth, 2011, 2012) and one corpus study (von der Malsburg, Kliegl, Vasishth, under revision). The experiments investigated how readers process temporarily ambiguous sentences. We showed that readers do not always commit to one of the alternative interpretations, and that readers with low working-memory capacity do so less often. Contrary to what was reported earlier, we found that reparsing instead of targeted repair is a common strategy to recover from incorrect interpretations. Interestingly, these results did not emerge in an analysis using traditional word-based eyetracking measures showing their limitations. In the corpus study, we demonstrated how syntax, oculomotor constraints, and age of reader jointly determine the regularity of scanpaths. We argue that, taken together, these results establish the scanpath as an informative and tractable object of investigation in reading research.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2013ECEM_scanpaths</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Co-registration of eye movements and brain potentials as a tool for research on reading and language comprehension</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Metzner, P., Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Metzner, P., Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2013). Co-registration of eye movements and brain potentials as a tool for research on reading and language comprehension. In K. Holmqvist, F. Mulvey, &amp; R. Johansson, Proceedings of the 17th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. 462). Lund, Sweden: Journal of Eye Movement Research.

Recent research demonstrated the feasibility of analyzing fixation-related brain potentials (FRPs) recorded during natural reading (Kretzschmar et al., 2009; Dimigen et al., 2011). Two questions arise from these studies: (1) Are effects observed with fixation-triggered EEG signals comparable to those observed in standard RSVP designs? (2) Does the combined analysis of EEG and fixation data provide additional insights into reading and comprehension processes that are not available with either method alone? Both above-mentioned studies used material known to robustly elicit strong N400 effects. The present study (N=50) examined responses to a more subtle manipulation representative of common experimental designs: we manipulated the distance between anaphoric expressions (pronouns, verb ellipsis) and their antecedents. Differences were examined using a non-parametric Monte Carlo test (Maris \&amp; Oostenveld, 2007). Increased distance of the antecedent elicited an early frontocentral negativity in response to verb ellipses (88ms-134ms, p&amp;lt;0.001) and a negativity at frontocentral and parietal electrodes on the words following pronouns (98ms-186ms, p&amp;lt;0.001). We discuss these results in the context of earlier findings and argue that adopting FRP-methodology requires factoring in complex visuomotor contingencies that are not yet fully understood and that evoke ERP effects different from those seen in RSVP designs.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2013ECEM_coreg</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Different coping strategies in sentence processing can be disentangled using coregistered eye movements and brain potentials</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2014). Different coping strategies in sentence processing can be disentangled using coregistered eye movements and brain potentials. In , Proceedings of the Sixth Annual Society for the Neurobiology of Language Conference (pp. ). Amsterdam, Netherlands: Society for the Neurobiology of Language.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2014SNL</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The relationship between regressive saccades and the P600 effect: Evidence from concurrent eye movement and EEG recordings</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2014). The relationship between regressive saccades and the P600 effect: Evidence from concurrent eye movement and EEG recordings. In N. Patson, S. Speer, L. Squires, R. Turnbull, L. Wagner, &amp; A. Walker, Proceedings of the 27th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Columbus, OH, USA: Ohio State University.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2014CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Recovering from syntactic and semantic violations: the relationship between eye movements and brain responses</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2014). Recovering from syntactic and semantic violations: the relationship between eye movements and brain responses. In M. Corley, H. Rabagliati, M. Nieuwland, P. Sturt, M. Pickering, &amp; A. Martin, Proceedings of the 20th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. 101). Edinburgh, UK: University of Edinburgh.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2014AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dem Gehirn zuhören</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Illing, C.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Illing, C. (2014). Dem Gehirn zuhören.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgIlling2014</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using co-registration of eye movements and event-related brain potentials to study the processing of anaphoric dependencies</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Metzner, P., Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Metzner, P., Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2014). Using co-registration of eye movements and event-related brain potentials to study the processing of anaphoric dependencies. In N. Patson, S. Speer, L. Squires, R. Turnbull, L. Wagner, &amp; A. Walker, Proceedings of the 27th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. 187). Columbus, OH, USA: Ohio State University.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2014CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brain Decompositions</title>
  <author>Illing, C., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Illing, C., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2014). Brain Decompositions.</description>
  <guid>IllingMalsburg2014</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>False-positive rates in eyetracking studies with multiple dependent measures</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B. (2015). False-positive rates in eyetracking studies with multiple dependent measures. In E. Kaiser, T. Mintz, R. Pancheva, &amp; J. Zevin, Proceedings of the 28th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Los Angeles, CA, USA: University of Southern California.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgAngele2015CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brain Decomposition</title>
  <author>Illing, C., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Illing, C., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). Brain Decomposition.</description>
  <guid>IllingMalsburg2015</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Py-Span-Task: A software for testing working memory span</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). Py-Span-Task: A software for testing working memory span.</description>
  <guid>Malsburg2015PySpanTask</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpath: An R package for analyzing scanpaths</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). Scanpath: An R package for analyzing scanpaths.</description>
  <guid>Malsburg2015Scanpath</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Saccades: An R package for detecting fixations in raw eye tracking data</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). Saccades: An R package for detecting fixations in raw eye tracking data.</description>
  <guid>Malsburg2015Saccades</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Keith Rayner eye movements in reading data collection</title>
  <author>Rayner, K., Abbott, M. J., Schotter, E. R., Belanger, N. N., Higgins, E. C., Leinenger, M., von der Malsburg, Titus, …</author>
  <description>Rayner, K., Abbott, M. J., Schotter, E. R., Belanger, N. N., Higgins, E. C., Leinenger, M., von der Malsburg, Titus, … (2015). Keith Rayner eye movements in reading data collection.</description>
  <guid>RaynerEtAl2015</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brain responses to world-knowledge violations: A comparison of stimulus- and fixation-triggered event-related potentials and neural oscillations</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2015). Brain responses to world-knowledge violations: A comparison of stimulus- and fixation-triggered event-related potentials and neural oscillations. Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience, 27(5), 1017–1028. http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/jocn_a_00731

Recent research has shown that brain potentials time-locked to fixations in natural reading can be similar to brain potentials recorded during rapid serial visual presentation (RSVP). We attempted two replications of Hagoort, Hald, Bastiaansen, and Petersson [Hagoort, P., Hald, L., Bastiaansen, M., \&amp; Petersson, K. M. Integration of word meaning and world knowledge in language comprehension. Science, 304, 438–441, 2004] to determine whether this correspondence also holds for oscillatory brain responses. Hagoort et al. reported an N400 effect and synchronization in the theta and gamma range following world knowledge violations. Our first experiment (n = 32) used RSVP and replicated both the N400 effect in the ERPs and the power increase in the theta range in the time–frequency domain. In the second experiment (n = 49), participants read the same materials freely while their eye movements and their EEG were monitored. First fixation durations, gaze durations, and regression rates were increased, and the ERP showed an N400 effect. An analysis of time–frequency representations showed synchronization in the delta range (1–3 Hz) and desynchronization in the upper alpha range (11–13 Hz) but no theta or gamma effects. The results suggest that oscillatory EEG changes elicited by world knowledge violations are different in natural reading and RSVP. This may reflect differences in how representations are constructed and retrieved from memory in the two presentation modes.</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2015N400</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How presentation modality influences reading comprehension</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., Metzner, P., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., Metzner, P., &amp; Levy, R. (2015). How presentation modality influences reading comprehension. In E. Kaiser, T. Mintz, R. Pancheva, &amp; J. Zevin, Proceedings of the 28th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Los Angeles, CA, USA: University of Southern California.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2015CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The influence of foreshadowing metaphors in a crime story by Ian Fleming</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Joseph, H., Troscianko, E., Kukkonen, K., &amp; Nation, K.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Joseph, H., Troscianko, E., Kukkonen, K., &amp; Nation, K. (2015). The influence of foreshadowing metaphors in a crime story by Ian Fleming. In A. Gatt, &amp; H. Mitterer, Proceedings of the 21th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Valetta, Malta: University of Malta.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2015AMLaP-Fleming</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The impact of reading modality on sentence comprehension</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Levy, R. (2015). The impact of reading modality on sentence comprehension. In A. Gatt, &amp; H. Mitterer, Proceedings of the 21th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Valetta, Malta: University of Malta.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2015AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Determinants of scanpath regularity in reading</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Kliegl, R., &amp; Vasishth, S. (2015). Determinants of scanpath regularity in reading. Cognitive Science, 39(7), 1675–1703. http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/cogs.12208

Scanpaths have played an important role in classic research on reading behavior. Nevertheless, they have largely been neglected in later research—perhaps also due to a lack of suitable analytical tools. Recently, von der Malsburg and Vasishth (2011) proposed a new measure for quantifying differences between scanpaths and demonstrated that this measure can recover effects that were missed with the traditional eyetracking measures. However, the sentences used in that study were difficult to process and scanpath effects accordingly strong. The purpose of the present study was to test the validity, sensitivity, and scope of applicability of the scanpath measure using simple sentences that are typically read straight from left to right. We derived predictions for the regularity of scanpaths from the literature on oculomotor control, sentences processing, and cognitive aging and tested these predictions using the scanpath measure and a large database of eye movements (N=230). All predictions were confirmed: sentences with short words and syntactically more difficult sentences elicited more irregular scanpaths. Also, older readers produced more irregular scanpaths than younger readers. In addition, we found an effect that was not reported earlier: syntax had a smaller influence on the eye movements of older readers than on those of young readers. We discuss this interaction of syntactic parsing cost with age in terms of shifts in processing strategies and a decline of executive control as readers age. Overall, our results demonstrate the validity and sensitivity of the scanpath measure and thus establish it as a productive and versatile tool for reading research.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2015</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The rules of statistics make no exception for reading research: False positive rates in eyetracking studies of reading behavior</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B. (2015). The rules of statistics make no exception for reading research: False positive rates in eyetracking studies of reading behavior. In A. Gatt, &amp; H. Mitterer, Proceedings of the 21th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Valetta, Malta: University of Malta.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgAngele2015AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>False-positive rates in eyetracking studies with multiple dependent measures</title>
  <author>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). False-positive rates in eyetracking studies with multiple dependent measures. In M. Perea, M. Vergara-Martínez, E. M. Rosa Martínez, P. Tejero, J. Roca Ruíz, I. Fajardo, L. Salmerón, …, Proceedings of the 12th Symposium of Psycholinguistics (pp. ). Valencia, Spain: Universitat de Valencia.</description>
  <guid>AngeleMalsburg2015SymPsych</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Multiple comparisons and false positive rates in eye tracking studies of reading behavior</title>
  <author>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). Multiple comparisons and false positive rates in eye tracking studies of reading behavior. In P. Gomez, &amp; W. Krenzer, Proceedings of the Pre-Psychonomics Word Recognition Conference (pp. ). Chicago, IL, USA: DePaul University, Chicago.</description>
  <guid>AngeleMalsburg2015Psychonomics</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>False positives in standard analyses of eye movements in reading</title>
  <author>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2015). False positives in standard analyses of eye movements in reading. In U. Ansorge, T. Ditye, A. Florack, &amp; H. Leder, Proceedings of the 18th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Vienna, Austria: Journal of Eye Movement Research.

Standard analyses of eye movements in reading test a set of canonical dependent measures calculated for multiple regions. Although the resulting multiple comparisons increase the rate of false positive results, it is accepted standard practice not to correct for that. We investigated false positives rates through computer simulations and tested how much statistical power has to be sacrificed to control them. In 100.000 iterations, we generated six realistic data sets of eye movements for a hypothetical experiment with typical parameters. The true effect sizes of the manipulation ranged from 0 ms to 40 ms. Four standard measures were analyzed using linear mixed models: first fixation duration, gaze duration, go-past time, and total viewing time. In the data sets with no true effect, the rate of false positives was 12.1%, i.e. much higher than the conventionally accepted 5%. A Bonferroni correction reduced false positives to 3.2% and was therefore slightly more conservative than required. The reduction in power due to the Bonferroni correction was moderate, e.g., from 90% to 75% for effect sizes of 5 ms. Contrary to conventional wisdom, the Bonferroni correction seems to be an appropriate tool for controlling false positives in reading experiments.</description>
  <guid>AngeleMalsburg2015ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Multiple comparisons and false positive rates in eye tracking studies of reading behaviour</title>
  <author>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Angele, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2016). Multiple comparisons and false positive rates in eye tracking studies of reading behaviour. In M. T. Bajo, Proceedings of the International Meeting of the Psychonomic Society (pp. 112). Granada, Spain: Psychonomic Society.</description>
  <guid>AngeleMalsburg2016Psychonomics</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dissociating influences of parafoveal and foveal information on reading: Forced fixations and comprehension.</title>
  <author>Schotter, L., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schotter, L., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2016). Dissociating influences of parafoveal and foveal information on reading: Forced fixations and comprehension. In R. Maki, Proceedings of the 21th Conference of the Psychonomic Society (pp. ). Boston, Massachusetts: Psychonomic Society.</description>
  <guid>SchotterEtAl2016Psychonomics</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Resumptive pronouns hinder sentence comprehension in english</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2016). Resumptive pronouns hinder sentence comprehension in english. In M. Carreiras, S. Mancini, N. Molinaro, D. Davidson, S. Caffarra, &amp; C. Martin, Proceedings of the 22th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. 98). Bilbao, Spain: Basque Center on Cognition, Brain and Language.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2016AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The importance of reading naturally: Evidence from combined recordings of eye movements and electric brain potentials</title>
  <author>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F.</author>
  <description>Metzner, P., von der Malsburg, Titus, Vasishth, S., &amp; Rösler, F. (2016). The importance of reading naturally: Evidence from combined recordings of eye movements and electric brain potentials. Cognitive Science, 41(S6), 1232–1263. http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/cogs.12384

How important is the ability to freely control eye movements for reading comprehension? And how does the parser make use of this freedom? We investigated these questions using coregistration of eye movements and event-related brain potentials (ERPs) while participants read either freely or in a computer-controlled word-by-word format (also known as RSVP). Word-by-word presentation and natural reading both elicited qualitatively similar ERP effects in response to syntactic and semantic violations (N400 and P600 effects). Comprehension was better in free reading but only in trials in which the eyes regressed to previous material upon encountering the anomaly. A more fine-grained ERP analysis revealed that these regressions were strongly associated with the well-known P600 effect. In trials without regressions, we instead found sustained centro-parietal negativities starting at around 320 ms post-onset, however, these negativities were only found when the violation occurred in sentence-final position. Taken together, these results suggest that the sentence processing system engages in strategic choices: In response to words that don’t match built-up expectations, it can either explore alternative interpretations (reflected by regressions, P600 effects, and good comprehension) or pursue a &amp;quot;good-enough&amp;quot; processing strategy that tolerates a deficient interpretation (reflected by progressive saccades, sustained negativities, and relatively poor comprehension).</description>
  <guid>MetznerEtAl2016</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The president gave her inauguration speech: explicit belief and implicit expectations in language production and comprehension</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2017). The president gave her inauguration speech: explicit belief and implicit expectations in language production and comprehension. In M. Baptista, &amp; A. Coetzee, 91th Annual Meeting of the Linguistics Society of America (pp. ). Austin, Texas: Linguistic Society of America.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2017LSA</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Parafoveal and foveal information serve different purposes in reading: parafoveal is used for saccade programming, foveal for comprehension</title>
  <author>Schotter, E., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schotter, E., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2017). Parafoveal and foveal information serve different purposes in reading: parafoveal is used for saccade programming, foveal for comprehension. In E. Gibson, I. Blank, E. Fedorenko, R. Futrell, M. Kline, &amp; R. Ryskin, Proceedings of the 30th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boston, MA, USA: Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</description>
  <guid>SchotterEtAl2017CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: resumptive pronouns in english help production but hinder comprehension</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2017). This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: resumptive pronouns in english help production but hinder comprehension. In E. Gibson, I. Blank, E. Fedorenko, R. Futrell, M. Kline, &amp; R. Ryskin, Proceedings of the 30th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boston, MA, USA: Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2017CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The president will give her inauguration speech: explicit belief and implicit expectations in language production and comprehension</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2017). The president will give her inauguration speech: explicit belief and implicit expectations in language production and comprehension. In E. Gibson, I. Blank, E. Fedorenko, R. Futrell, M. Kline, &amp; R. Ryskin, Proceedings of the 30th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boston, MA, USA: Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2017CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The president gave her inauguration speech. No, they didn’t! The interaction of explicit world knowledge, implicit gender stereotypes, and discourse expectations</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2017). The president gave her inauguration speech. No, they didn’t! The interaction of explicit world knowledge, implicit gender stereotypes, and discourse expectations. In G. v. Bergen, &amp; J. Spenader, Proceedings of Discourse Expectations: Theoretical, Experimental and Computational perspectives (DETEC 2017) (pp. ). Nijmegen, Netherlands: Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2017DETEC</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The impact of forced fixations on word recognition: dissociation of oculomotor behavior and linguistic processing</title>
  <author>Schotter, L., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schotter, L., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2017). The impact of forced fixations on word recognition: dissociation of oculomotor behavior and linguistic processing. In H. Deubel, A. Nuthmann, S. Martinez-Conde, R. Radach, S. Everling, &amp; U. Ettinger, Proceedings of the 19th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Wuppertal, Germany: Journal of Eye Movement Research.</description>
  <guid>SchotterEtAl2017ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Automatic reading (obfuscation)</title>
  <author>Schurer, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schurer, B., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2017). Automatic reading (obfuscation). In L. Ribas, &amp; R. Taveira, Proceedings of the fifth conference on Computation, Communication, Aesthetics and X (pp. ). Lisbon, Portugal: The xCoAx 2017 organizing committee.

During reading, we rapidly construct meaning from sequences of rather cryptic symbols. A multitude of processes are involved in making meaning happen, however, most of them are conveniently tucked away from the reader’s conscious experience allowing them to read effortlessly without having to worry about any of the practicalities such as where to place the gaze next and for how long. The present work reflects on the marvelous feat that is reading. In an experiment-like situation, we create a perceptual short-circuit that unlocks the otherwise unconscious processes involved in reading. To this end, the test subject is exposed to a written libretto while a computer tracks their eye movements and translates them to sound in real time. The artistic implementation is based on parametric synthesis (“mapping”) and model-based sonification.</description>
  <guid>SchurerMalsburg2017xCoAx</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>False positives and other statistical errors in standard analyses of eye movements in reading</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Angele, B. (2017). False positives and other statistical errors in standard analyses of eye movements in reading. Journal of Memory and Language, 94(), 119–133. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jml.2016.10.003

In research on eye movements in reading, it is common to analyze a number of canonical dependent measures to study how the effects of a manipulation unfold over time. Although this gives rise to the well-known multiple comparisons problem, i.e.~an inflated probability that the null hypothesis is incorrectly rejected (Type I error), it is accepted standard practice not to apply any correction procedures. Instead, there is a widespread belief that corrections are not necessary because the increase in false positives is too small to matter. To our knowledge, no formal argument has ever been presented to justify this assumption. Here, we report a computational investigation of this issue using Monte Carlo simulations. Our results show that, contrary to conventional wisdom, false positives are increased to unacceptable levels when no corrections are applied. Our simulations also show that counter-measures like the Bonferroni correction keep false positives in check while reducing statistical power only moderately. Hence, there is little reason why such corrections should not be made a standard requirement. Further, we discuss two statistical illusions that can arise when statistical power is too low, and we show how power can be improved to prevent these illusions. In sum, our work renders a detailed picture of the various types of statistical errors than can occur in studies of reading behavior and we give concrete guidance about how these errors can be avoided.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgAngele2017</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder comprehension</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2018). This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder comprehension. In M. Pickering, M. Crocker, R. Hartsuiker, V. Ferreira, H. Branagan, &amp; R. Mishra, Proceedings of the 1th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference - Asia (pp. ). Hyderabad, Telangana, India: University of Hyderabad.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2018AMLaPAsia</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Expectations and prediction in sentence comprehension: German particle verbs as a test case</title>
  <author>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2018). Expectations and prediction in sentence comprehension: German particle verbs as a test case. In F. Ferreira, J. Henderson, T. Swaab, &amp; M. Traxler, Proceedings of the 31th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: UC Davis.</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2018CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder comprehension</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2018). This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder comprehension. In F. Ferreira, J. Henderson, T. Swaab, &amp; M. Traxler, Proceedings of the 31th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: UC Davis.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2018CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2018). Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences. In F. Ferreira, J. Henderson, T. Swaab, &amp; M. Traxler, Proceedings of the 31th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: UC Davis.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2018CUNY2</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Semantic attraction in sentence processing</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2018). Semantic attraction in sentence processing. In F. Ferreira, J. Henderson, T. Swaab, &amp; M. Traxler, Proceedings of the 31th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: UC Davis.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2018CUNY1</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Implicit gender biases in the production and comprehension of pronominal references</title>
  <author>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2018). Implicit gender biases in the production and comprehension of pronominal references. In F. Ferreira, J. Henderson, T. Swaab, &amp; M. Traxler, Proceedings of the 31th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Davis, CA, USA: UC Davis.</description>
  <guid>BoyceEtAl2018CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction in german SOV structures: An ERP study</title>
  <author>Schäfer, R., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Lago, S.</author>
  <description>Schäfer, R., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Lago, S. (2018). Agreement attraction in german SOV structures: An ERP study. In P. Knoeferle, Proceedings of the 24th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Berlin, Germany: Humboldt Universität Berlin.</description>
  <guid>SchaeferEtAl2018AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>English resumptive pronouns do not help the comprehender</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2018). English resumptive pronouns do not help the comprehender. In P. Knoeferle, Proceedings of the 24th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Berlin, Germany: Humboldt Universität Berlin.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2018AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gender-biases in language processing: Explicit beliefs about event outcomes vs. implicit linguistic expectations</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Boyce, V., Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Boyce, V., Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2018). Gender-biases in language processing: Explicit beliefs about event outcomes vs. implicit linguistic expectations. In P. Knoeferle, Proceedings of the 24th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Berlin, Germany: Humboldt Universität Berlin.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2018AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Semantic attraction in sentence processing</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2018). Semantic attraction in sentence processing. In P. Knoeferle, Proceedings of the 24th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Berlin, Germany: Humboldt Universität Berlin.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2018AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder sentence comprehension</title>
  <author>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2018). This is the structure that we wonder why anyone produces it: Resumptive pronouns in English hinder sentence comprehension. In , California Meeting on Psycholinguistics (CAMP) (pp. ). Los Angeles, USA: UC Los Angeles.</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2018CAMP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When your mind ignores what your eyes see: How forced fixations lead to comprehension illusions in reading</title>
  <author>Schotter, E., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schotter, E., Leinenger, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2018). When your mind ignores what your eyes see: How forced fixations lead to comprehension illusions in reading. Psychonomic Bulletin \&amp; Review, 25(5), 1884–1890. http://dx.doi.org/10.3758/s13423-017-1356-y

The phenomenon of forced fixations suggests that readers sometimes fixate a word (due to oculomotor constraints) even though they intended to skip it (due to parafoveal cognitive-linguistic processing). We investigate whether this leads readers to look directly at a word but not pay attention to it. We used a gaze-contingent boundary paradigm to dissociate parafoveal and foveal information (e.g., the word phone changed to scarf once the reader&amp;apos;s eyes moved to it) and asked questions about the sentence to determine which one the reader encoded. When the word was skipped or fixated only briefly (i.e., up to 100 ms) readers were more likely to report reading the parafoveal than the fixated word, suggesting that there are cases in which readers look directly at a word but their minds ignore it, leading to the illusion of reading something they did not fixate.</description>
  <guid>SchotterEtAl2018b</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Forced fixations, trans-saccadic integration, and word recognition: Evidence for a hybrid mechanism of saccade triggering in reading</title>
  <author>Schotter, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Leinenger, M.</author>
  <description>Schotter, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Leinenger, M. (2018). Forced fixations, trans-saccadic integration, and word recognition: Evidence for a hybrid mechanism of saccade triggering in reading. Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition, 45(5), 677–688. http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/xlm0000617

Recent studies using the gaze-contingent boundary paradigm reported a reversed preview benefit – shorter fixations on a target word when an unrelated preview was easier to process than the fixated target (Schotter \&amp; Leinenger, 2016). This is explained via forced fixations – short fixations on words that would ideally be skipped (because lexical processing has progressed enough) but could not be because saccade planning reached a point of no return. This contrasts with accounts of preview effects via trans-saccadic integration – shorter fixations on a target word when the preview is more similar to it (see Cutter, Drieghe, \&amp; Liversedge, 2015). Additionally, if the previewed word – not the fixated target – determines subsequent eye movements, is it also this word that enters the linguistic processing stream? We tested these accounts by having 24 subjects read 150 sentences in the boundary paradigm in which both the preview and target were initially plausible but later one, both, or neither became implausible, providing an opportunity to probe which one was linguistically encoded. In an intervening buffer region, both words were plausible, providing an opportunity to investigate trans-saccadic integration. The frequency of the previewed word affected progressive saccades (i.e., forced fixations) as well as when trans-saccadic integration failure increased regressions, but, only the implausibility of the target word affected semantic encoding. These data support a hybrid account of saccadic control (Reingold, Reichle, Glaholt, \&amp; Sheridan, 2012) driven by incomplete (often parafoveal) word recognition, which occurs prior to complete (often foveal) word recognition.</description>
  <guid>SchotterEtAl2018</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ERP evidence for long-distance lexical predictions in German particle verb constructions</title>
  <author>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2019). ERP evidence for long-distance lexical predictions in German particle verb constructions. In E. Colunga, A. Kim, L. Michaelis, &amp; B. Narasimhan, Proceedings of the 32th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boulder, CO, USA: University of Colorado Boulder.</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2019CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ERP evidence of object agreement attraction in comprehension</title>
  <author>Schäfer, R., Lago, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Schäfer, R., Lago, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2019). ERP evidence of object agreement attraction in comprehension. In E. Colunga, A. Kim, L. Michaelis, &amp; B. Narasimhan, Proceedings of the 32th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boulder, CO, USA: University of Colorado Boulder.</description>
  <guid>SchaeferEtAl2019CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction effects in the comprehension of grammatical sentences</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2019). Agreement attraction effects in the comprehension of grammatical sentences. In E. Colunga, A. Kim, L. Michaelis, &amp; B. Narasimhan, Proceedings of the 32th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boulder, CO, USA: University of Colorado Boulder.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2019CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Remember ‘him’, forget ‘her’: Gender bias in the comprehension of pronominal referents</title>
  <author>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2019). Remember ‘him’, forget ‘her’: Gender bias in the comprehension of pronominal referents. In E. Colunga, A. Kim, L. Michaelis, &amp; B. Narasimhan, Proceedings of the 32th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Boulder, CO, USA: University of Colorado Boulder.</description>
  <guid>BoyceEtAl2019CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Comprehenders generate long-distance predictions during reading: erp evidence from verb-particle constructions</title>
  <author>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2019). Comprehenders generate long-distance predictions during reading: erp evidence from verb-particle constructions. In M. Whelpton, J. Jalbert, A. Beretta, S. Sigurjónsdóttir, Þ. Eyþórsson, Ó. Jóhannesson, A. Shaw, …, Proceedings of Psycholinguistics in Iceland -- Parsing and Prediction (pp. ). Reykjavík, Iceland: University of Iceland.</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2019PIPP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Female gender is consistently under-expressed in pronoun production and under-inferred in comprehension</title>
  <author>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>Boyce, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. (2019). Female gender is consistently under-expressed in pronoun production and under-inferred in comprehension. In R. Pancheva, &amp; K. Iskarous, 93th Annual Meeting of the Linguistics Society of America (pp. ). New York, NY, USA: Linguistic Society of America.

Language production and comprehension draw on wide-ranging knowledge and beliefs, including general world knowledge and contextually variable information. Pronominal references to role nouns with diverse gender biases provide a window into the interplay of these sources of information: violations of stereotypical gender elicit surprise (e.g., referring to a surgeon as she), but comprehenders can accommodate to non-stereotypical genders within discourse. In two experiments, we investigate how gender expectations are reflected in production and comprehension of pronominal references to role nouns. Our results indicate that female gender is consistently underused in English pronoun production, and under-inferred in English pronoun comprehension.</description>
  <guid>BoyceEtAl2019LSA</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Implicit gender bias in linguistic descriptions for expected events: The cases of the 2016 United States and 2017 United Kingdom elections</title>
  <author>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. P.</author>
  <description>von der Malsburg, Titus, Poppels, T., &amp; Levy, R. P. (2020). Implicit gender bias in linguistic descriptions for expected events: The cases of the 2016 United States and 2017 United Kingdom elections. Psychological Science, 31(2), 115–128. http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0956797619890619

Gender stereotypes influence subjective beliefs about the world, and this is reflected in our use of language. But do gender biases in language transparently reflect subjective beliefs? Or is the process of translating thought to language itself biased? During the 2016 United States (N = 24,863) and 2017 United Kingdom (N = 2,609) electoral campaigns, we compared participants? beliefs about the gender of the next head of government with their use and interpretation of pronouns referring to the next head of government. In the United States, even when the female candidate was expected to win, she pronouns were rarely produced and induced substantial comprehension disruption. In the United Kingdom, where the incumbent female candidate was heavily favored, she pronouns were preferred in production but yielded no comprehension advantage. These and other findings suggest that the language system itself is a source of implicit biases above and beyond previously known biases, such as those measured by the Implicit Association Test.</description>
  <guid>MalsburgEtAl2020</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Contextual constraint and the frontal post-N400 positivity: A large-sample, pre-registered ERP study</title>
  <author>Stone, K., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Stone, K., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2020). Contextual constraint and the frontal post-N400 positivity: A large-sample, pre-registered ERP study. In M. Breen, B. Dillon, L. Frazier, J. Kingston, S. Momma, &amp; A. Staub, Proceedings of the 33th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Amherst MA, USA: University of Massachusetts, Amherst.</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2020CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reading strategies in monolingual adults and children vs. bilingual heritage and l2 speakers of Russian: a scanpath analysis</title>
  <author>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2020). Reading strategies in monolingual adults and children vs. bilingual heritage and l2 speakers of Russian: a scanpath analysis. In T. {von der Malsburg}, S. Vasishth, &amp; I. Wartenburger, Proceedings of the 26th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: Universität Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>ParshinaEtAl2020AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using eye movements to index reading comprehension ability</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2020). Using eye movements to index reading comprehension ability. In T. {von der Malsburg}, S. Vasishth, &amp; I. Wartenburger, Proceedings of the 26th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: Universität Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2020AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Lewis and Vasishth model predicts agreement and semantic attraction effects in acceptability judgments, but not in response times</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2020). The Lewis and Vasishth model predicts agreement and semantic attraction effects in acceptability judgments, but not in response times. In T. {von der Malsburg}, S. Vasishth, &amp; I. Wartenburger, Proceedings of the 26th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: Universität Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2020AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Different sources of predictions during natural reading: an EEG and eye-tracking co-registration study</title>
  <author>Bianchi, B., Loredo, R., Carden, J., Jaichenco, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Shalom, D., &amp; Kamienkowski, J.</author>
  <description>Bianchi, B., Loredo, R., Carden, J., Jaichenco, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Shalom, D., &amp; Kamienkowski, J. (2020). Different sources of predictions during natural reading: an EEG and eye-tracking co-registration study. Journal of Vision, 20(11), 1308–1308. http://dx.doi.org/10.1167/jov.20.11.1308

During reading our brain predicts upcoming words. If predictions are correct, words can be processed faster when they are finally fixated. It has been amply shown that Predictability (the variable that estimates the probability of guessing the next word) have an impact on how we move our eyes across the text and that it modulates brain potentials associated with word processing. On the one side, more predictable words are fixated for shorter periods of time than less predictable words. On the other side, more predictable words correspond to less N400 amplitude. This knowledge comes from separated EEG and eye movement experiments, but in the last few years, co-registration experiments enabled us to test these hypotheses together in more natural contexts. With the aim of investigating different sources of predictions during reading, in previous studies, we showed that mnemonic predictions (i.e. predictions performed purely on long term memory, like when reading a proverb or a song lyric) and predictions done purely on the linguistic context have different impact, both on gaze duration and on the N400. Here, we asked participants to read proverbs and common sentences while we recorded EEG and eye movements simultaneously. Firstly, we analysed brain activity aligned to fixation onset (fixation-related potential, FRPs) showing differences between Proverbs and Common sentences in late potentials evoked by low- and high-Predictable words. Secondly, we analysed oscillations aligned to fixation onset (fixation-related spectral perturbations, FRSPs) showing differences between sentence type only in low-frequency bands after 200ms. These results extend our knowledge of the differences between the mechanisms involved in the prediction of the following word.</description>
  <guid>BianchiEtAl2020VSS</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The effect of decay and lexical uncertainty on processing long-distance dependencies</title>
  <author>Stone, K., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Stone, K., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2020). The effect of decay and lexical uncertainty on processing long-distance dependencies. PeerJ, (), 8–10438. http://dx.doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/xrm43</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2020</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quadruplex negatio invertit? The on-line processing of depth charge sentences</title>
  <author>Paape, D., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Paape, D., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2020). Quadruplex negatio invertit? The on-line processing of depth charge sentences. Journal of Semantics, 37(4), 509–555. http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jos/ffaa009</description>
  <guid>PaapeEtAl2020</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shared syntax between comprehension and production: Multi-paradigm evidence that resumptive pronouns hinder comprehension</title>
  <author>Morgan, A. M., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V. S., &amp; Wittenberg, E.</author>
  <description>Morgan, A. M., von der Malsburg, Titus, Ferreira, V. S., &amp; Wittenberg, E. (2020). Shared syntax between comprehension and production: Multi-paradigm evidence that resumptive pronouns hinder comprehension. Cognition, 205(), 104417. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cognition.2020.104417</description>
  <guid>MorganEtAl2020</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A comparison of three reading comprehension tests using eye movements</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2020). A comparison of three reading comprehension tests using eye movements. In C. Connor, Proceedings of the Twenty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading (pp. ). Irvine, CA 92616-5999 USA: Society for the Scientific Study of Reading.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2020SSSR</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bias against “she” pronouns can be rapidly overcome by changing event expectations</title>
  <author>Poppels, T., Boyce, V., Ajunwa, C., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>Poppels, T., Boyce, V., Ajunwa, C., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Levy, R. (2021). Bias against “she” pronouns can be rapidly overcome by changing event expectations. In J. Trueswell, D. Dahan, A. Papafragou, G. Roberts, K. Schuler, F. Schwarz, &amp; C. Yang, Proceedings of the 34th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States: University of Pennsylvania.</description>
  <guid>PoppelsEtAl2021CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using eye movements to predict performance on reading comprehension tests</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2021). Using eye movements to predict performance on reading comprehension tests. In J. Trueswell, D. Dahan, A. Papafragou, G. Roberts, K. Schuler, F. Schwarz, &amp; C. Yang, Proceedings of the 34th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States: University of Pennsylvania.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2021CUNY</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences arises only in the good-enough processing mode</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; Titus von der Malsburg</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; Titus von der Malsburg (2021). Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences arises only in the good-enough processing mode. In J. Trueswell, D. Dahan, A. Papafragou, G. Roberts, K. Schuler, F. Schwarz, &amp; C. Yang, Proceedings of the 34th Annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States: University of Pennsylvania.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2021</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monolingual and heritage bilingual strategies in reading in Russian</title>
  <author>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2021). Monolingual and heritage bilingual strategies in reading in Russian. In A. Andrychowicz-Trojanowska, I. Banasiak, S. Bonacchi, A. Borowska, M. Kaliska, D. Kudła, A. Leńko-Szymańska, …, Proceedings of the 13th International Symposium on Bilingualism (ISB13) (pp. ). Warsaw, Poland: University of Warsaw.</description>
  <guid>ParshinaEtAl2021ISB</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Can eye movements be used to predict reading comprehension ability?</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2021). Can eye movements be used to predict reading comprehension ability? In G. Turco, G. Thiberge, C. Pozniak, T. Poppels, B. Hemforth, S. Colonna, &amp; A. Abeillé, Proceedings of the 27th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Paris, France: Université de Paris.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2021AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bias against &amp;quot;she&amp;quot; pronouns can be rapidly overcome by changing event expectations</title>
  <author>Poppels, T., Boyce, V., Ajunwa, C., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Levy, R.</author>
  <description>Poppels, T., Boyce, V., Ajunwa, C., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Levy, R. (2021). Bias against &amp;quot;she&amp;quot; pronouns can be rapidly overcome by changing event expectations. In G. Turco, G. Thiberge, C. Pozniak, T. Poppels, B. Hemforth, S. Colonna, &amp; A. Abeillé, Proceedings of the 27th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). Paris, France: Université de Paris.</description>
  <guid>PoppelsEtAl2021AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences arises only in the good-enough processing mode</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2021). Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences arises only in the good-enough processing mode. In , Proceedings of Linguistic Illusions in Sentence Processing 2021 (pp. ). Konstanz, Germany: .</description>
  <guid>LaurinvichyuteMalsburg2021LISP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring recall as an ecologically-valid measure of reading comprehension</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2021). Exploring recall as an ecologically-valid measure of reading comprehension. In K. Cain, C. Wood, J. Ricketts, &amp; L. Wade-Woolley, Proceedings of the Twenty-Eighth Annual Meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading (pp. ). : Society for the Scientific Study of Reading.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2021SSSRb</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using eye movements to predict reading comprehension scores</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2021). Using eye movements to predict reading comprehension scores. In K. Cain, C. Wood, J. Ricketts, &amp; L. Wade-Woolley, Proceedings of the Twenty-Eighth Annual Meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading (pp. ). : Society for the Scientific Study of Reading.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2021SSSRa</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Incremental language comprehension difficulty predicts activity in the language network but not the multiple demand network</title>
  <author>Wehbe, L., Blank, I. A., Shain, C., Futrell, R., Levy, R., von der Malsburg, Titus, Smith, N., …</author>
  <description>Wehbe, L., Blank, I. A., Shain, C., Futrell, R., Levy, R., von der Malsburg, Titus, Smith, N., … (2021). Incremental language comprehension difficulty predicts activity in the language network but not the multiple demand network. Cerebral Cortex, (), . http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhab065</description>
  <guid>WehbeEtAl2021</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An entropy-based approach to measuring morphological productivity</title>
  <author>Pankratz, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Pankratz, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2022). An entropy-based approach to measuring morphological productivity. In C. Maienborn, &amp; M. Averintseva-Klisch, 44st Annual Conference of the German Linguistic Society (pp. ). Tübingen, Germany: .</description>
  <guid>PankratzEtAl2022DGfS</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpath regularity as a measure of reading comprehension ability</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2022). Scanpath regularity as a measure of reading comprehension ability. In N. McIntyre, I. Coombs, A. Peters, T. Törmänen, &amp; L. Catrysse, Proceedings of the EARLI Special Interest Group on Online Measures of Learning Processes (SIG27) (pp. ). Southampton, England: University of Southampton.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2022SIG27</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpath regularity as a predictor of performance on reading comprehension assessments</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2022). Scanpath regularity as a predictor of performance on reading comprehension assessments. In D. Barrett, V. McGowan, A. Pagan, K. Paterson, F. Proudlock, D. Souto, &amp; M. Thomas, Proceedings of the 21th European Conference on Eye Movements (ECEM) (pp. ). Leicester, England: University of Leicester.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2022ECEM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shannon entropy is a more comprehensive and principled morphological productivity measure than the standard alternatives</title>
  <author>Pankratz, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Pankratz, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2022). Shannon entropy is a more comprehensive and principled morphological productivity measure than the standard alternatives. Unpublished manuscript.</description>
  <guid>PankratzEtAl2022MS</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Does entropy modulate the prediction of German long-distance verb particles?</title>
  <author>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Stone, K., Vasishth, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2022). Does entropy modulate the prediction of German long-distance verb particles? PLOS ONE, (), .</description>
  <guid>StoneEtAl2022</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Monolingual and bilingual reading strategies in Russian: An exploratory scanpath analysis</title>
  <author>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Parshina, O., Sekerina, I., Lopukhina, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2022). Monolingual and bilingual reading strategies in Russian: An exploratory scanpath analysis. Reading Research Quarterly, 57(2), . http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/rrq.414</description>
  <guid>ParshinaEtAl2022</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Semantic attraction in sentence comprehension</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2022). Semantic attraction in sentence comprehension. Cognitive Science, 46(2), 13086. http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/cogs.13086</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2022</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction effects depend on the processing goal</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2023). Agreement attraction effects depend on the processing goal. In T. Warren, S. Fraundorf, M. W. Dickey, N. Tokowicz, &amp; S. Wiener, Proceedings of the 36th Annual Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Pittsburgh, USA: University of Pittsburgh.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteEtAl2023HSP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Neural bases of predictions during natural reading of known statements: an electroencephalography and eye movements co-registration study</title>
  <author>Bianchi, B., Loredo, R., Fonseca, M. d., Carden, J., Jaichenco, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Shalom, D. E., …</author>
  <description>Bianchi, B., Loredo, R., Fonseca, M. d., Carden, J., Jaichenco, V., von der Malsburg, Titus, Shalom, D. E., … (2023). Neural bases of predictions during natural reading of known statements: an electroencephalography and eye movements co-registration study. Neuroscience, 519(), 131–146. http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2023.03.024</description>
  <guid>BianchiEtAl2023</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dependency length minimization in SOV languages: A bounded rationality view</title>
  <author>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2023). Dependency length minimization in SOV languages: A bounded rationality view. In S. Husain, &amp; A. Verma, The South Asian Forum on the Acquisition and Processing of Language (pp. ). Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh, India: Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur.</description>
  <guid>RanjanMalsburg2023SAFAL</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Patterns in the phonology of Mandarin Chinese: Basic color terms and beyond</title>
  <author>Hole, D., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Hole, D., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2023). Patterns in the phonology of Mandarin Chinese: Basic color terms and beyond. Unpublished manuscript.</description>
  <guid>HoleMalsburg2023MS</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The role of goal in sentence processing</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2023). The role of goal in sentence processing. In M. Carreiras, C. Martin, A. Stoehr, I. Quiñones, S. Mancini, A. Carrión-Castillo, E. Kapnoula, …, Proceedings of the 29th Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing Conference (AMLaP) (pp. ). San Sebastián, Spain: Basque Center on Cognition, Brain, and Language.

The role of goal has largely been ignored in sentence processing research, presumably because (morpho-)syntactic processing is assumed to be invariant to goal, which is not necessarily true. In a series of four single-trial self-paced reading experiments manipulating task and sentence grammaticality, we show that: 1) in grammatical sentences like 1a and 1b, no effect is observed at the verb when participants expect to answer comprehension questions, but a slowdown in condition 1b (attraction effect) arises when participants expect to judge acceptability; 2) in ungrammatical sentences like 1c and 1d, agreement attraction (speedup at the verb+1 in 1d) is present irrespective of the task, but the effect changes direction at the verb+2 when participants expect to judge sentence acceptability. Typically-observed reading time effects (attraction in 1c vs. 1d, no effect in 1a vs. 1b) occur when the goal is answering comprehension questions but disappear when the goal is acceptability judgment. Instead, judgment-typical effects appear. Overall, agreement attraction demonstrates a surprising degree of task-dependency. 1. (a) The candidate that the lobbyist openly supports ... (b) The candidates that the lobbyist openly supports ... (c) The candidate that the lobbyist openly *support ... (d) The candidates that the lobbyist openly *support ...</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteEtAl2023AMLaP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A bounded rationality account of dependency length minimization in Hindi</title>
  <author>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2023). A bounded rationality account of dependency length minimization in Hindi. In M. Goldwater, F. Anggoro, B. Hayes, &amp; D. Ong, Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (pp. ). Sidney, Australia: Cognitive Science Society.</description>
  <guid>RanjanMalsburg2023CogSci</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Predicting recall performance from eye movements during normal reading</title>
  <author>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D., Yu, L., Reichle, E., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2023). Predicting recall performance from eye movements during normal reading. In G. McArthur, A. Castles, &amp; R. Parrila, Proceedings of the Twenty-Seventh Annual Meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading (pp. ). Port Douglas, Queensland, Australia: Society for the Scientific Study of Reading.</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2023SSSR</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Scanpath regularity as an index of reading comprehension</title>
  <author>Mézière, D. C., Yu, L., McArthur, G., Reichle, E. D., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Mézière, D. C., Yu, L., McArthur, G., Reichle, E. D., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2023). Scanpath regularity as an index of reading comprehension. Scientific Studies of Reading, 0(0), 1–22. http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/10888438.2023.2232063</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2023b</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using eye-tracking measures to predict reading comprehension</title>
  <author>Mézière, D. C., Yu, L., Reichle, E. D., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G.</author>
  <description>Mézière, D. C., Yu, L., Reichle, E. D., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; McArthur, G. (2023). Using eye-tracking measures to predict reading comprehension. Reading Research Quarterly, 58(3), 425–449. http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/rrq.498</description>
  <guid>MeziereEtAl2023</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction effects depend on the goal of processing</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S.</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., Yadav, H., von der Malsburg, Titus, &amp; Vasishth, S. (2024). Agreement attraction effects depend on the goal of processing. In D. Georgi, I. Wartenburger, A. Gafos, A. Hölzl, &amp; R. B. Araujo, Proceedings of Linguistic Evidence 2024 (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: University of Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteEtAl2024LE</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>It’s not just all in the head: Towards a processing model of German adjective-noun-noun constructions and the bracketing paradox</title>
  <author>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). It’s not just all in the head: Towards a processing model of German adjective-noun-noun constructions and the bracketing paradox. In D. Georgi, I. Wartenburger, A. Gafos, A. Hölzl, &amp; R. B. Araujo, Proceedings of Linguistic Evidence 2024 (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: University of Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>PryslopskaMalsburg2024LE</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A bounded rationality account of constituent order in SOV languages</title>
  <author>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Ranjan, S., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). A bounded rationality account of constituent order in SOV languages. In D. Georgi, I. Wartenburger, A. Gafos, A. Hölzl, &amp; R. B. Araujo, Proceedings of Linguistic Evidence 2024 (pp. ). Potsdam, Germany: University of Potsdam.</description>
  <guid>RanjanMalsburg2024LE</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Towards a psycholinguistic model of bracketing paradoxes</title>
  <author>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). Towards a psycholinguistic model of bracketing paradoxes. In J. Boland, J. Brennan, L. Levinson, R. Lewis, &amp; S. Namboodiripad, Proceedings of the 37th Annual Conference on Human Sentence Processing (pp. ). Ann Arbor, USA: University of Michigan Ann Arbor.</description>
  <guid>PryslopskaMalsburg2024HSP</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Towards a psycholinguistic model of bracketing paradoxes</title>
  <author>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Prysłopska, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). Towards a psycholinguistic model of bracketing paradoxes. In A. Papafragou, &amp; F. Schwarz, Proceedings of Experiments in Linguistic Meaning (pp. ). Philadelphia, PA 19104-6228: Linguistic Society of America.</description>
  <guid>PryslopskaMalsburg2024ELM</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The role of conversational principles in cognitive biases: The case of overprecision in interval estimation</title>
  <author>Meyer, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Meyer, M., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). The role of conversational principles in cognitive biases: The case of overprecision in interval estimation. Unpublished manuscript.</description>
  <guid>MeyerMalsburg2024MS</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences and the role of the task</title>
  <author>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus</author>
  <description>Laurinavichyute, A., &amp; von der Malsburg, Titus (2024). Agreement attraction in grammatical sentences and the role of the task. Journal of Memory and Language, (), .</description>
  <guid>LaurinavichyuteMalsburg2024</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
